Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Housing Serials TAM.729
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Housing Serials
1925-2002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Housing Foundation (New York, N.Y.)
New England Free Press
Lower East Side Joint Planning Council
Bronx Tenants Union
Cambridge Tenants Organizing Committee
TAM.729
2 Linear Feet 2 flat boxes, 1 record carton, and 1 manuscript box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Housing Serials groups 74 titles relating to housing originally received by the Tamiment Library through subscriptions, donations, and as part of archival collections. The majority of the collection consists of incomplete runs of newspapers and newsletters published by tenant associations, co-op federations, and neighborhood groups across the Northeastern United States between 1950-2000. Additionally, there are serials and pamphlets produced by agencies addressing planning, eviction, and homelessness, and a handful of titles from elsewhere in the US and from the United Kingdom. The serials address issues of living conditions, urbanization, and gentrification, often in the broader context of social movements happening more widely; there is also discussion of everyday community news more generally, with some titles including sections in Spanish. No complete runs of publications are contained herein, and generally only a handful of issues of each publication are held.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection combines serials relating to housing drawn from two discrete groups of material held by the Tamiment Library. The first was a partially inventoried backlog of serials received by the library through donations, subscriptions, and in archival collections. The second group consisted of around 1,700 serials, newspapers, and magazines, organized by title as an artificial collection, referred to as Periodicals.001 or Boxed Newspapers. This material was combined, inventoried, and arranged and described in subject-based categories in 2017. The accession number related to this collection is 2017.049.
Arrangement
Material is arranged at the file level, in alphabetical order by publication title, with issues of each publication organized chronologically. Each title is listed alongside its publishing organization and city of origin, where available.
Scope and Contents
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Housing Serials assembles partial runs of 74 publications addressing issues around housing, published between 1925 and 2002 mainly in the United States. The majority of the collection consists of newspapers and newsletters distributed by community organizations, alongside self-produced pamphlets, circulars, and one-off reports containing guidance from agencies addressing problems in housing. The serials document exchanges between government agencies and tenants' groups, relaying news of changes in housing law, standards governing living conditions, discriminatory renting practices, rent strikes, gentrification, squatting, and homelessness. Some titles record events in neighborhoods acutely impacted by changes in the availability and quality of housing, chronicling communities in the Bronx, Morningside Heights, Fort Greene, and the Lower East Side, New York; Somerville, Brockton, and Newton Centre, Massachusetts; and in the Bay Area of California and Seattle, Washington. Among the organizations whose publications are included are the Bronx Tenants Union; the Lower East Side Joint Planning Council; the Architects' Renewal Committee in Harlem; the Cambridge Tenants' Organizing Committee; the Amalgamated Housing Corporation; the United Housing Foundation; and Jobs or Income Now (JOIN). The majority of serials date between around 1970-1995, with a handful of earlier titles; smaller areas of the collection include single publications from London, England, and Toronto, Canada, and a report on the conditions of housing in the United States published in Switzerland. Publications often also cover neighborhood and community news more generally, addressing issues around jobs, transit, police brutality and anti-racism efforts, and some include Spanish-language sections. No complete runs of publications are contained herein, and generally only a handful of issues of each publication are held.
Homelessness -- United States.; Housing -- United States.; Housing -- Periodicals.; Public housing -- United States.; Housing, Cooperative -- United States -- 20th century.; Tenants' associations.; Urban renewal -- United States.
- 30 Day Notice: The Union, Seattle, WA, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 30 Years of Amalgamated Cooperative Housing 1927-1957: Amalgamated Housing Corporation, Bronx, NY, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Alumni Cooperator: Inter-Cooperative Council, Ann Arbor, MI, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- At Home with JPC: Lower East Side Joint Planning Council, New York, NY, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Block Development Project: Block Development Project, New York, NY, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Building Together: New York, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bulletin-Morningside Gardens: Morningside Heights Cooperative/Morningside Heights Housing Corp., New York, NY, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Cambridge Tenants' Newsletter: Cambridge Tenants' Organizing Committee, Boston, MA, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Camden Tenant: Camden Federation of Tenants and Residents Associations, London, England, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- City Limits: Association of New Brotherhood Housing Developers, New York, NY, 1981-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
- City News: Hagedorn Communications, Inc., Bronx, NY, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Colloquium: Newsletter of Research in Daily Life: Research in Daily Life, New York, NY, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Community News: Amalgamated Housing Corp, Bronx, NY, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- CommUnity News, Boston, MA, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Community Times, West Lafayette, IN, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Co-Op Activity: Co-Op Education Guild, New York, NY, 1962-1968 (Box Shared Tamiment 053, Folder 1)
- Co-op Bulletin: Potomac Co-op Federation, Washington, DC, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Co-Op Chapter: Cooperative Institute Association, New York Area Chapter, New York, NY, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Co-op City Times: Co-op City Times, Bronx, NY, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Co-op Contact: United Housing Foundation, New York, NY, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Cooperator: United Housing Foundation, New York, NY, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Crisis: Alliance for Housing, Jobs, and Education, Philadelphia, PA, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Eastern Cooperatives: Eastern Cooperative Wholesale, Inc., New York, NY, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Fort Greene Tenants Voice: Fort Greene Tenants Association, Brooklyn, NY, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Free Press: Somerville Tenants' Union, Somerville, MA, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Handbook on the 1975 Rent Increase: Cambridge Tenants' Organinizing Committee, Cambridge, MA (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Hands Off the Homeless: Revolutionary Communist Party, New York Branch, New York, NY, circa 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Harlem News: Architects' Renewal Committee in Harlem, New York, NY, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 27, Box 2, Folder 8)
- 'Heights and 'Valley News: Columbia Tenants Union, New York, NY, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Home Front: Action for the Homeless, Inc., Baltimore, MD, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 28, Box 3, Folder 7)
- Home Front: People's Homesteading Group Inc., Baltimore, MD, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Homes for All: Homes for All, Oakland, CA, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Housing & Jobs: A Blueprint for Survival: Jobs with Peace, Boston, MA, circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Housing America: The National Council for the Social Studies, Washington, DC, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Housing Justice Campaign: Housing Justice Campaign, New York, NY, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Les Conditions de Logement aux Etats-Unis: Bureau International du Travail, Geneva, Switzerland, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Life without Landlords: New Outlook Publishers, New York, NY, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Lincoln Park Press: Concerned Citizens Survival Front, Chicago, IL, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Madison Tenant Union News: West Bronx Tenants Union, Bronx, NY, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Mass. Tenant: Massachusetts Tenants Organizing Committee, MA, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Metaviction: M Grandino, Santa Cruz, CA, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Metropolitan Council on Housing Papers: Metropolitan Council on Housing, New York, NY, 1967-1988 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Morningside Gardens News: Morningside Gardens Tenant-Cooperators Committee, New York, NY, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 40, Box 3, Folder 1-6)
- Neighborhood Works: Center for Neighborhood Technology, Inc., Chicago, IL, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- News: Not a Penny on the Rent: United Tenants Action Committee, Great Britain, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Newsletter: Jobs or Income Now (JOIN), Chicago, IL, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Notes on the Bench: Committee to Re-Elect Judge Margaret Cammer, Inc., Brooklyn, NY, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Organizing Development of a Federal Housing Tenant Union: San Francisco, CA, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Peoples Press: News and Views of the Lower East Side Joint Planning Council: Lower East Side Joint Planning Council, New York, NY, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Public Housing Progress: National Public Housing Conference, New York, NY, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Public Policy Principles: Interfaith Assembly on Homelessness and Housing, New York, NY, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Rent Strikes in New York: New England Free Press, Somerville, MA, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Report from your Board of Directors: Morningside Heights Housing Corp., New York, NY, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Reporte de La Ocupacion: One Purse, New York, NY, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Safety Network: Coalition for the Homeless, New York, NY, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 51, Box Shared Tamiment 053, Folder 2)
- Sea-Town Crier: Sea-Town Crier, Seattle, WA, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Shelter: Committee of Responsibility, Newton Centre, MA, circa 1973 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Slum Dweller: Lower East Side Public Housing Conference, New York, NY, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Somerville Free Press: Somerville Tenants Union, Somerville, MA, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- STIC: San Francisco Tenant Issues Council, San Francisco, CA, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Tenant Report: Tenants Union of the West Side, Inc., New York, NY, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Tenants Against America: The War, the Master Plan, the Law, Evictions: Berkeley Tenants Union, Berkeley, CA, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Tenants Arising: Ithaca Tenants Union, Ithaca, NY, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- The Tenants Association Council of Boston Public Housing: Stephen M. Scholnick, Boston, MA, circa 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Tenants First: Newsletter for FHA Tenants: Coalition of FHA Tenant Unions throughout Massachusetts, Cambridge, MA, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Tenants Handbook: Legal Tactics: Cambridge Tenants' Organinizing Committee, Cambridge, MA, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Tenants News: Brockton Tenants Union, Brockton, MA, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 63, Box Shared Tamiment 053, Folder 3)
- Tenants' Newsletter: Cambridge Tenants' Organinizing Committee, Cambridge, MA, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Tenants United: Bronx Tenants Union, Bronx, NY, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Title 1: Slum Clearance Progress; Committee on Slum Clearance Progress, New York, NY, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- The War Against the Poor...Spatial Deconcentration!, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Trefann Court News: Trefann Court Residents' Association, Toronto, Canada, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- United Tenant: United Tenants Assn., London, England, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Who's Moving: Regional Young Adult Project, San Francisco, CA, circa 1973 (Box 1, Folder 69, Box Shared Tamiment 053, Folder 4)
- Working Paper: Tenants Action Group, Boston, MA, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 70)